ABHINAV VERMA

(971) 200-5014 o verma@utexas.edu https://averma8053.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research lies at the intersection of machine learning and formal methods. I am especially concerned with building trustworthy intelligent systems, using learning models that are provably safe, human interpretable, reliable, and robust to domain shifts.

EMPLOYMENT

Institute of Science and Technology Austria

August 2021 - August 2022

Postdoc o Henzinger Group

Pennsylvania State University

Hartz Family Career Development Assistant Professor Department of Computer Science and Engineering August 2022 - onward University Park, PA

EDUCATION

University of Texas at Austin

Ph.D. student o Computer Science Advisor: Prof. Swarat Chaudhuri

Mavisor. 1 for. Swarat Chaudhar

Indian Institute of Science

 $M.S. \circ Mathematics$

July 2011 Bangalore, India

University of Delhi - Hindu College

B.A. Honors • Mathematics

June 2008 New Delhi, India

August 2021

Austin, TX

PUBLICATIONS

Google Scholar Profile: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jM1HeCIAAAAJ

Peer-Reviewed

1. Programmatically Interpretable Reinforcement Learning

<u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Vijayaraghavan Murali, Rishabh Singh, Pushmeet Kohli, Swarat Chaudhuri 35th International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**) 2018.

Acceptance Rate: 29.1%

Accepted as a Long Talk: Top 9% of submitted papers.

2. Representing Formal Languages: A Comparison of Finite Automata and Recurrent Neural Networks

Joshua J. Michalenko, Ameesh Shah, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Swarat Chaudhuri, Ankit B. Patel 7th International Conference on Learning Representations (**ICLR**) 2019.

Acceptance Rate: 31.4%

3. Control Regularization for Reduced Variance Reinforcement Learning Richard Cheng, Abhinav Verma, Gábor Orosz, Swarat Chaudhuri, Yisong Yue, Joel W. Burdick 36th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2019. Acceptance Rate: 22.6%

4. Imitation-Projected Programmatic Reinforcement Learning Abhinav Verma, Hoang M. Le, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2019. Acceptance Rate: 21.6%

5. Learning Differentiable Programs with Admissible Neural Heuristics Ameesh Shah, Eric Zhan, Jennifer J Sun, Abhinav Verma, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%

6. Neurosymbolic Reinforcement Learning with Formally Verified Exploration Greg Anderson, Abhinav Verma, Isil Dillig, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%

Technical Report

• Verifiable and Interpretable Reinforcement Learning through Program Synthesis Abhinav Verma

Doctoral Consortium at The 33rd AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) 2019.

Masters Thesis

• Irreducible Representations Of The Symmetric Group And The General Linear Group Abhinav Verma

Department of Mathematics at The Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 2011.

AWARDS & HONORS

- Fellowship, J.P. Morgan AI Research PhD Fellowship 2020. \$100,000 award to support tuition, stipend, and travel.
- Research Award, Dean Award, School of Engineering, Rice University 2019.
- Bronze Medal, ACM Student Research Competition at Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) 2018.
- Bronze Medal, ACM Student Research Competition at The 45th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL) 2018.
- Fellowship, Council of Scientific & Industrial Research (NSF-Equivalent), India 2011.
- Scholarship, Ministry of Human Resource Development, India 2008-2010.

MENTORING

Six students co-advised, three from underrepresented groups, two associated publications.

Current

• Masters, Surva S Dwivedi, University of Texas at Austin. Project: Reinforcement learning for F1Tenth cars.

• Undergraduate, Myra Cheng, Caltech. Project: Machine learning for behavioral neuroscience.

Abhinav Verma - CV 2 of 5 • Undergraduate, Joshua Deng, University of Texas at Austin.

Project: Learning programmatic models of RNA splicing.

Graduated

• Masters, Ameesh Shah, Rice University.

Project: Learning differentiable programs with admissible neural heuristics.

Currently: Graduate Student at UC Berkeley.

• Undergraduate, Jacqui Lee, Rice University.

Project: Adaptive therapies for Sepsis via reinforcement learning.

Currently: Graduate Student at MIT.

• Intern, Nirha Patel, University of California, San Diego.

Project: Evolutionary algorithms for reinforcement learning.

Currently: Developer at Yahoo.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Rice University

January 2017 - December 2019

Teaching Assistant

- COMP 539: Software Engineering Methodology.

 Project based graduate course on software engineering.
- COMP 503: Reasoning About Software.

Graduate course on formal methods and automated reasoning.

• COMP 310: Advanced Object-Oriented Programming and Design. Senior undergraduate course on OOP.

Wolfram Research

January 2015 - August 2016

Certified Instructor

- Conducted online corporate training for Mathematica users.
- Helped develop and improve courses based on newly introduced functionality.

University of Oregon

September 2012 - June 2014

Standalone Instructor

Approximately forty students in each class.

- Math 105: University Mathematics.
 - Introduction to logic, combinatorics, and probability.

Core requirement for BS degree.

- Math 111: College Algebra.
 - Foundational course in algebra, functions, and mathematical modeling.

Calculus preparation course, prerequisite for higher-level math courses.

• Math 112: Elementary Functions.

Focus on mathematical induction and trigonometric functions.

Precalculus designed for math, biology, physiology, and CS majors.

Teaching Assistant

Abhinav Verma - CV 3 of 5

• Math 243: Introduction to Probability and Statistics. Undergraduate course on statistical reasoning.

Dr. B. R. Ambedkar University

January 2012 - April 2012

Teaching Assistant

• M01: Introduction to Mathematical Thinking. First course on abstract mathematics.

INDUSTRIAL EXPERIENCE

SRI International

June 2019 - August 2019

Research Intern, Mentor: Susmit Jha

Menlo Park, CA

- Researched interpretable reinforcement learning via program synthesis.
- Integrated vision models with programmatic reinforcement learning.

Microsoft Research

June 2017 - September 2017

Research Intern, Mentor: Christoph M. Wintersteiger

Cambridge, UK

- Researched methods to use deep neural networks for quantifier instantiation in Z3.
- Intern in the Programming Principles and Tools group.

Wolfram Research

August 2014 - August 2016

Champaign, IL

Technology Engineer

- Researched integrating automated theorem proving into the Wolfram Language.
- Helped identify and implement new functionality based on cutting edge research.

AuntyCook

August 2011 - July 2012

Co-Founder New Delhi, India

- Conceptualized a business, creating a marketplace for the sale of home cooked meals.
- Used machine learning to optimize sales and deliveries.

SERVICE

Referee

- The 38th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2021.
- The 9th International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2021.
- Machine Learning (Springer Journal).
- The 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020.
- The 23rd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2020.
- The 32nd International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV) 2020.
- The 12th NASA Formal Methods Symposium (NFM) 2020.

Committees

University of Texas, Austin

Abhinav Verma - CV 4 of 5

• Junior Graduate Admissions Committee: responsible for initial screening of PhD applications.

Rice University

- Graduate Student Faculty Search Committee: responsible for feedback on faculty candidates.
- School of Engineering Co-op management committee.

Indian Institute of Science

- PC Member, Conference on Algebraic and Combinatorial Representation Theory.
- Student Committee, Indian Institute of Science Centenary Conference.

Delhi University

• Member Central Council: governing body of student union with fifty thousand members.

INVITED TALKS

- Henzinger Group Seminar, Institute of Science and Technology Austria, April 2021.
- Institute for Foundations of Machine Learning Seminar, UT Austin, November 2020.
- Neurosymbolic Learning Seminar, University of Pennsylvania, October 2020.

INVITED PARTICIPATION

- The New York Academy of Sciences, 14th Annual Machine Learning Symposium 2020.
- International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, Virtual 2020.
- International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV), New York 2019.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Long Beach 2019.
- International Conference on Learning Representations, New Orleans 2019.
- International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, Vancouver 2019.
- Doctoroal Consortium at AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Honolulu 2019.
- Deep Learning and Reinforcement Learning Summer School, University of Alberta 2019.
- Marktoberdorf Summer School on Engineering Secure and Dependable Software Systems 2018.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Stockholm, Sweden 2018.
- Rice University Machine Learning Seminar, 2018.
- Wolfram Technology Conference, Champaign, Illinois 2014.
- Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, University of Colorado, Boulder 2014.
- Graduate Student Topology and Geometry Conference, University of Texas, Austin 2014.
- Pacific Northwest Geometry Seminar, Stanford University 2014.
- Midwest Dynamical Systems Meeting, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2013.
- Workshop on Unitary Representations of Real Reductive Groups, University of Utah 2013.
- Graduate Student Topology and Geometry Conference, University of Notre Dame 2013.
- International Congress of Mathematicians (ICM), Hyderabad, India 2010.
- Conference on Algebraic and Combinatorial Approaches to Representation Theory, Bangalore, India 2010.
- Conference on Groups, Actions, Computations (GAC), Allahabad, India 2010.
- Conference on Analysis and its Applications, Bangalore, India 2009.

Abhinav Verma - CV 5 of 5